A beautiful day, flat calm sea and a thousand gannets over your head.
I can't wipe the grin off my face!
The Shetland Islands, as far north as you can get in the British Isles.
A land heaving with wildlife.
It's been my dream to get to know Shetland through the seasons of a year with my family.
Have a see!
Thank you.
To watch and film the extraordinary, dynamic wildlife.
I'm on the trail of some of Britain's rarest birds.
Oh, look, look, look, look, look!
And the mighty killer whales are back.
Shetland has some of the most extraordinary wildlife in Britain.
This is a dream place for me.
My family and I first came to Shetland a year ago.
There's a crab!
Since then, we've been back here through the seasons...
From the wild winter...
Whoa, that is deep!
Through the glorious spring.
And now it's midsummer and our final stay here.
Shetland is the most northerly point in Britain.
The archipelago is made up of over 100 islands where you're never more than three miles from the sea.
At this time of year, there are millions of wild creatures making the most of the long days to raise their families.
In midsummer you get over 19 hours of sunlight.
One of the very best places for seabirds here is Sumburgh Head on the southern tip of the mainland.
It's 10 o'clock at night but there's still plenty of light to film by.
I've come here with my wife Marguerite, who's also a filmmaker.
We're hoping to witness an event which only happens on a few evenings each year in midsummer.
It's something neither one of us has ever seen before.
We've come right down to the southernmost point in Shetland to the guillemot colonies here with a view to, I hope, witnessing a really astonishing event.
The moment when the chicks leave the nest.
What makes it so astonishing?
Well, they can't fly when they do it.
They haven't got any feathers, they've just got fluff.
And they're going to have to jump from the cliff ledge where they were raised down into the sea below...which seems bonkers!
Guillemots are common in Shetland, but their life story is anything but ordinary.
Each pair raises a single chick in the summer.
But whereas most seabird chicks don't leave the nest until they have feathers and can fly properly, young guillemots are just three weeks old and downy when they leave.
I love the name they're given.
They're called jumplings as opposed to fledglings, which is just perfect.
They haven't got any feathers, so they cane fledglings, so they're a jumpling.
Perfect.
But just when they go is unpredictable.
Oh, there's a chick right there.
Yeah, really close.
See if I can get it here.
Until now, these chicks' entire world has been the tiny cliff ledge where they've been raised and fed by Mum and Dad.
But all that's about to end.
Over the next couple of weeks, all of them will have to make the jump of their lives...
50 feet down the side of the cliff to the sea below.
And to add to their problems, the nest colonies are patrolled by great skuas, bonxies, looking for an easy meal.
As the evening wears on, there are fewer predators like bonxies still up and about and that's why the guillemots choose to coax their chicks down to the sea at this late hour.
It's gone half past ten at night, but there's still plenty of light.
Oh, look!
There's one following its dad.
Definitely.
Yeah, there he is.
He's got the chick with him.
Dad's going to flutter down.
Very excited-looking father.
It's always the adult male alone that guides the chick to the water.
The chick's mother has nothing more to do with her youngster.
A long way down to the sea.
Look at the way the baby hugging its dad.
Sweet...
Oh, oh, oh!
It looks like the point of no return doesn't it?
Got nowhere else to slide.
There goes Dad.
Is he going to go?
Come on, little guy.
He's going to go.
Yeah!
Splosh.
Ha, ha!
Sweet.
Seeing that chick make the leap of faith, literally the leap of faith, because its father had gone in the water and that's it, no choice now.
No going back up the cliff to the nest ledge, because it's not got the wings to do the job.
And bounce like a little cork off the surface of the sea.
And they're away.
They're swimming off into the sunset, literally in to the sunset.
The very first time this chick has hit the water and it's able to swim like a professional.
Other chicks and their fathers are thinking about making a move.
As they walk through the colony, they have to deal with neighbours, all defending their tiny patch of cliff ledge from intruders.
Every step is fraught with danger.
Another one coming down.
Where?
Same place.
I can't see the chick.
The chick's below.
Has it gone?
It fell.
It fell below in front of us, look.
Yes, got it.
I wonder if some ever die falling down.
They're so light I don't think they ever come a cropper by hitting a rock.
But they can fall into a place where they can't escape.
And that would mean starvation, so if they fall between two rocks or in a crevice that they can't escape from, then yeah, that would be the end of it.
Oh, slipping.
Ooh...
Look, he's going to go straight.
He's definitely going to slip.
This chick is desperate to find his way back to its dad.
No wonder the father's looking so anxious.
Oh, dear.
He's in.
Phew!
A brutal and dramatic entry into the marine world for the chick, but this is just the start.
Because now, father and chick will paddle all the way to the coast of Norway - some 200 miles away!
It will take them weeks and along the way the chick will grow, learn to fly and feed itself by diving for fish.
And just why the Shetland guillemots make this epic journey?
A midsummer's night.
In Shetland this time is called the simmer dim.
There's nothing else like it in Britain.
It's idyllic.
The simmer dim.
It's now half past twelve in the middle of the night.
Beautiful red sunset sky.
I don't know whether to call it a sunset or sunrise because it's not going to disappear.
The sun is just skimming below the horizon and within a few hours it's going to be back up again.
And literally not a breath of wind and I can hear so many different birds.
All of them busy, busy, busy and that's why this place is so rich for life.
That's why there are so many birds nesting here.
They don't run out of the day.
The day continues round the clock and they make the most of this short season to raise their families before the winter closes in and they move off.
This is pure, pure magic.
A beautiful summer's morning and we're heading for the island of Noss.
It makes sense to make it a day out for the whole family.
Noss is one of the finest nature reserves in Britain.
Nicknamed Seabird City, home to thousands of our biggest and most dynamic seabirds, gannets.
Over the past year we've been following the family fortunes of these birds.
In the winter we fixed two remote cameras near a gannet's nest.
Abseiling down a 600-foot cliff to do so.
In the spring, we returned to see if any gannets had nested in view of the cameras.
A pair had taken up residence and they had an egg.
Jump in.
Most of the islands in Shetland are uninhabited, but this wasn't always the case.
There are signs of human settlement on Noss that date back to the Bronze Age 4000 years ago and the final settlers left for good in the 1970s.
I hope with the little remote camera, the nest we've been following from the beginning of the year, has got a healthy successful chick on it.
Gannets aren't the only birds nesting on Noss.
Everything from puffins to skuas breeds here and some, like great black backed gulls, are quick to defend their nests.
OK, here's the gull.
There's a chick just there, hiding in the grass.
You see the babies?
Watch your heads.
One of the ways they try to dissuade you is to fly very, very close and if you don't move off, they'll use their feet and hit you on the head and Savannah being the highest point, she'll get hit before I do.
So we're moving off.
Daddy!
Silly, silly birds.
They're rather sensible, you know.
Because they're telling us that we're a bit too close to their nest for their comfort.
The trek to the gannet cliffs is about 2 miles.
Uphill most of the way.
At last, we reach our destination.
Sleepy baby.
OK, it's just here.
This is where we fixed the remote cameras to the cliffs.
I have to find the cable ends for the cameras and connect them to a monitor, then we'll see if we have a chick on our nest.
Do you remember where that plug goes?
Mm-hm.
In there?
Can you do that?
Push even harder.
There we go.
Perfect.
That's the job.
Right now moment of truth.
One camera was looking down on the nest from above, the other was looking from the side.
I just hope they're still both working.
There's nothing there.
Is there anything there?
Oh, oh!
One of the cameras isn't working.
Ai-ai-ai-ai!
This is the other one.
This is our last chance, ready, Savannah.
What's on there?
Yeah!
We have got a picture.
Bit muzzy.
What's that?
That's the gannets.
That mummy and a daddy gannet.
And we have to see if they've got a chick.
That's the view looking straight down.
Can you see them?
I can see!
Yes there is.
There's a chick underneath her there.
I saw a fluffy edge just there.
Hey, they've got a baby.
They've got a chick and we've got a chick.
There are about 8000 pairs of gannets on the cliffs here and the sight, sound and smell of this throng of life is breathtaking.
This is looking like a good breeding year.
Lots of nests with chicks, a sign that there's plenty of fish in the sea.
Very promising.
These youngsters have a long way to go.
Unlike the guillemots, gannet chicks stay in the nest until they can fly, and that's at least three months away.
Our pair still has a lot of work to do.
It's super to see that they've got a hatched chick.
Not just a little one either, it's already well underway.
Really nice.
Each pair raises just one youngster a year, and it's touching to see the amount of care and dedication lavished by both parent birds on their chick.
It's astonishing to think that these bundles of fluff will become sleek avian dive bombers, beautifully adapted to plunge diving for fish up to 50 feet below the surface of the water.
But the speed with which they hit the water means it's all over in a flash.
I'd love to try and film gannets hunting in slow motion, to reveal what's really going on.
That's us the long trek back now.
But what a day.
Absolutely gorgeous and great to see that the gannet family have got a youngster.
Nobody fell off a cliff.
And you got us safe and sound.
Shetland attracts wildlife enthusiasts from all over the world, and it's a magnet for scientists too.
Today Marguerite and I are going on a trip with the North Atlantic Killer Whale Research Team.
They're gathering information about groups of killer whales that travel between Shetland, Iceland and Norway.
I've already been lucky enough to encounter some of these killer whales last summer.
First a lone bull, then later a group of males, females and calves hunting seals close to the shore.
Sightings like these are few and far between, so any opportunity to catch up with them is a must.
Just yesterday, the research team had contact with a large group of killer whales a few miles north of the Shetland coast and managed to record some of the remarkable sounds they make, using some rather innovative equipment.
Do you know what it is?
It's a wok.
It's fantastic.
It woks!
It's quite a cool thing.
The team have modified the wok, turning it into a directional underwater microphone.
Just yesterday, Volker Deecke recorded killer whales communicating with each other using his homemade hydrophone.
This one here.
Wee wop.
And then another one.
Is that the same animal do you think?
They're probably calling back and forth to each other.
Killer whales can sense their prey in a similar way to bats, by using echolocation.
But the team have discovered that they may also use sound in a very different way to hunt.
THUMP Oh, yeah.
Krr!
Is that the tail?
That's the tail....
Hitting fish.
The idea is, and it's still a working hypothesis, that this very loud call may be uncomfortable to herring.
When herring get uncomfortable, they school together, so this may be a tool to get the herring to school up.
And when they're all in a tight ball, they go whack and hit the whole school with the tail fin.
And then mop up the debilitated fish.
With whales having been sighted so recently, there's a strong chance they're still in the neighbourhood.
So today we're off on a boat trip to see if we can film them.
The research team has identified 26 individual killer whales around Shetland.
More seem to be coming into these waters, but they are still very hard to see.
We're going to need a bigger boat.
Yeah.
Most of this is our picnic, you realise.
Our plan today is for the research team to head out on their boat with the listening device, while we travel on a larger boat with local wildlife expert, Brydon Thomason.
Hopefully, between us, we'll pick up the killer whales.
The conditions are perfect so I really hope we find them.
We are heading past the very tip of the British Isles.
Muckle Flugga, the lighthouse, the most northerly point anyone has ever lived.
It's not manned any more as a lighthouse.
But Out Stack, that rock just off to the left is the last bit of land before you're out in the open sea.
You go any further north, you're in another country.
But this is where orcas are.
While the research team are using their hydrophone to listen out for the whales, we'll be relying on visual clues.
And, after half an hour's sailing, the signs we were looking for!
There's a big flock of birds feeding right on our heading now.
Where the gannets are feeding, there are fish.
Where there are fish, there might be killer whales.
Could be up ahead.
But beneath the birds, it's not the killer whales, it's a close relative of theirs.
Dolphins.
What?
Just coming towards us about 11 o'clock.
Got it, yeah.
Look at that.
White-sided dolphins, hundreds of them!
These are powerful fish hunters of cold north Atlantic waters, and the sea around Shetland is about the best place in Britain to see them.
They're fast, surging along at almost 30 miles an hour.
There's loads of splashing going on ahead up here.
We've got into a massive feeding group now of seabirds and dolphins.
Big big schools of white-sided dolphins.
The activity is spread right across the horizon.
There are pockets of birds feeding all over the place.
Big shoals of fish to support this much life.
Who knows...
Oh, beautiful breach just there.
That was lovely.
Great to have found the dolphins!
But no killer whales today and the research team haven't picked up any sounds either.
The whales will be back though and now we'll be on call with the whale research team.
I'm hopeful we'll see them before we leave the islands.
To move around Shetland's 15 inhabited islands, you need ferries.
They are very much part of life up here.
12 vessels make 190 sailings a day.
I'm off to one of the northern isles to film one of Britain's rarest birds, a creature with rather unconventional breeding habits.
The red-necked phalarope.
This is the spot, one of the few places in the British Isles where you can reliably see these gorgeous little birds, red-necked phalaropes.
They're incredibly rare, only about 25 males breed on Shetland so I have to have a special licence to film them.
Curious, facet of phalarope behaviour, is that they're waders, wading birds like oystercatchers and curlew, but they feed in a way a bit more like a seabird, and only come into these fresh water pools to breed.
I'll just put myself here and see what comes of it.
Couple of females right there.
But the most surprising thing about red-necked phalaropes, is that when it comes to raising a family, they reverse roles.
It's the males that brood the eggs and raise the chicks.
The females simply lay the eggs then clear off.
The female birds on the water in front of me may well have laid eggs in a nest already, but if they get the chance, they may try to get another male to mate with them, and leave him with a family to raise.
Truly liberated females.
(Wow. )
(Look at that. )
It's like a ballet.
Amazing to think that right in front of me now, is a good percentage of the British population of red-necked phalarope.
Oh, there's a male, I think.
The males are much less brightly coloured than the females.
He might well have just arrived from his migration and he's clearly worked up an appetite, paddling through the rich soup of tiny flies.
He's not going to get much peace though.
All these females want him to be the father of their eggs.
He's got something this lad.
Girls really having a bit of hair-pulling session, they're all desperately trying to chat him up.
And one female wins over all the rest.
She could well be the mother of the brood he'll be incubating.
She's effectively defending him against the attentions of other females.
Hands off girls, he's mine.
And with the pressure off from the other females, the male can concentrate on getting a meal again.
Soon the females will leave Shetland and head off to feed on the open sea.
The male's then are left to cope with the eggs on their own.
I'll come back to see how these single fathers manage.
I'm in heaven.
It's quite probably the finest phalarope evening I have ever had.
I'm a happy bunny.
Whether it's the detail in the lives of the wild creatures here, or the sheer scale of the wilderness, Shetland is a place that can suddenly turn your head, and you realise you are in one of the most beautiful places on earth.
The summer's weather has been exquisite, but the effect of the warm air passing over the cold sea here, causes great banks of mist to roll in from time to time.
It's put an end to my filming the wildlife for a day or two, but the break gives us the chance to meet Richard Grains.
I know the weather wasn't looking exactly onside was it?
No, should be ok though.
What do you think of this?
You're not going to hear the end of the whistle I don't think.
Richard's a crab fisherman, and he's invited us to come along for his last catch of the day.
Richard works the creels commercially for velvet swimming crab, lobster, whatever else comes up.
I just think it's great for Savannah to see part of what makes Shetland tick.
We're heading just off the shore, to where Richard cast his creels a couple of days ago.
Not that you can tell where the land is today!
Where's Shetland?
It's here somewhere.
We could be in the middle of the North Sea.
I've no idea.
Richard works single-handed, hauling up the creels or crab traps which have been sitting on the seabed.
What's that, Savannah?
Crabs, crabs crabs!
There's not much market for velvet crabs in the UK, so all of these will be exported live to Spain.
So how many do you normally haul on a day?
Sometimes 200, sometimes 300.
Wow!
200 or 300 creels in a day.
Just think of what that means in terms of physical effort.
Do you see these little bits at the back, these ones, they're paddles, it uses them for swimming.
Touch him and see what he feels like.
What does he feel like?
Soft.
Soft, exactly!
Soft and furry, because he's got fluff on his back.
That's why he's called a velvet swimming crab.
These are the largest swimming crabs in British waters and are a favourite food of otters.
Bye bye.
But it's not just crabs that find their way into the creels.
Oooh, what's on there?
It's a conger eel!
No chance.
Shall I move him out.
I'll put him back.
Oh, he's gone.
Look, Savannah, that's a sun star.
Wow, isn't that amazing?
It's missing one leg.
Shall I put him back?
Say, "Bye, bye, sun star."
Bye bye, sun star.
Richard returns the undersize crabs to the sea before baiting the creels and casting them back in.
He does this every day during the season, in all but the worst storms.
Fortunately the sea mist is short lived and we're back in blazing summer sunshine before long.
Just as well, because our time here is running out and there's so much I still want to see and film.
One of my big ambitions is to film seabirds with a super slow motion camera, especially gannets plunge diving.
But before we risk using the camera out at sea, we've come to the island of Mousa to test it out on the arctic tern colony here.
First, we have to get past the birds' defences, which include dive bombing and pooing on us.
There's a potential that we're going to get massively attacked by these terns.
We won't be in the colony, we'll walk around the edge but they're so keen to defend their chicks.
Ooh, look at him coming.
We're not even near them yet.
We're also very likely to get shat on.
Is that English, shat on?
Shat on, yes.
Are you sure?
Yes.
Or shat upon, actually.
Shat on.
Now I know what it means.
It smells of fish, strongly.
We've got the birds, now it's time to get the kit ready.
There are lots of elements of this set up to get right, so it's worth a last-minute check.
Marguerite is going to provide the action.
OK, thank you.
Lovely.
Yeah, you're definitely moving.
Whee, she can fly!
Wow, look at the lace movement.
Top lace movement.
It's nice though because it shows you the slowing down, it's brilliant.
The camera and computer are working fine.
Now I just have to plug in the viewfinder and we're ready to go.
POP!
Ah!
Did you hear that?
Yep.
That sounded like the viewfinder popping.
You cannot be serious.
A faulty power lead has blown up the viewfinder.
Try the other battery.
That is the other battery.
It blew.
I know it blew.
I absolutely know it blew.
Don't you want to try the first one again in case this battery is flat?
No, I don't.
Arghhhh!
A broken viewfinder makes it impossible for me to follow the action of the birds in flight.
All this gear, all this way, for nothing.
I wonder if there is anyone in Shetland who could fix it?
After a few phone calls, I've been directed to a repair shop in Lerwick.
A power drill and a big screwdriver.
Not your usual tools for a repair job on a £30,000 camera.
The person who owns this is going to look back at this and say, "What are they doing to my viewfinder?!"
Davie and Brian, between them in this Aladdin's cave of electrical wonders, are working hard to try to get a solution so that we can work tomorrow and hopefully, film the gannets or the skuas or anything, for that matter.
Oh, something came off.
What is that bit?
'It's soon obvious to Davie which bit has blown up.'
If you've got this on the shelf, I'll fall over backwards.
Any ideas, Brian?
I'd be surprised if we've got anything like that.
'Brian's had a bit of a rummage and thinks he may have a solution.'
It should work quite happily.
It's a different chip but it's doing a similar job.
If we can make this work, then we might be in business.
Well, we hope so anyway.
There's no guarantee this is going to work, mind you.
That's what we're working towards, making that thing fire up.
I'll get the other power.
Last Ditchology, that's where we are!
"Shetland Scrapstore, Incorporating Last Ditchology."
That says it all.
They're magicians, these guys.
Some things you can fix, some things you canna.
Listen for the pop-bang.
Is that smoke coming out there?
Look, we've got a viewfinder!
Y-e-e-es!
Well done!
How do we put it back together?
Fixed.
Well done, Brian.
Now it's fixed we'll need to kill you, because we don't want anyone to know how it's done!
Cheers, chaps.
Thanks very, very much indeed.
Superstars.
All the stars are lining up for us.
The weather is stunning again, the slow motion camera AND its viewfinder are working and Tom Jamieson who runs the Mousa Ferry has time to take us on his boat to try film gannets plunge-diving.
A gannet is never better illustrated its abilities as a hunter of the open seas than when you see it plunging for a fish.
And to do so 20 or 30 times slower than normal speed, well, that's just going to look magic.
Gannets range far and wide over the ocean, searching for shoals of fish, but to film them diving very close to the boat, I've brought a few boxes of mackerel.
And the best place to find gannets in Shetland?
The seas around Noss, the island where our gannet family is nesting, along with 17,000 neighbours!
Noss is a stunning, stunning seabird colony.
This is the cliff where we have our remote camera stationed, looking down at the nest.
So, our female is sitting on her chick up there somewhere.
You couldn't pick a better day to admire this great tower block of life.
The gannets here are used to following the fishing boats and picking off any stray catch.
They should come quickly to any fish I throw in the sea.
They're all coming in.
Good.
We got the birds, we got the weather, now we just have to have the equipment working...pleeeeeease!
So, Tom down in front of me here, please.
Yeah, nice.
Let's have a look at that.
Hold it.
We can instantly view the shots we get on the laptop computer.
So funky, isn't it, when you see them piling in like that?
Get ready, Madgy.
Let's have a look at that.
The gannets could be hitting the water in excess of 65 mph and they're perfectly adapted for the job.
They have no external nostrils so the water doesn't shoot up their nose.
They have special cushions in their foreheads to withstand the impact with the water's surface, and articulated shoulder joints that allow the wings to sweep back along the body, forming the perfect torpedo shape.
It's such a graphic form and so beautiful, and not only that but water always looks stunning in slow-mo, the splashes and the shine and the silver jewels.
Everything takes on a whole new atmosphere.
So yeah, I'm chuffed.
OK, Let's try another.
Oh, that was a good one!
Slowed down by 40 times, it's possible to fully appreciate the flexibility of these high-speed hunters, a sight that is exhilarating and impressive in life is transformed into a beautiful display of precision and grace.
Tom has to get back to ferry visitors over to the island of Mousa.
We still have half a box of mackerel left and in my view, the gannets deserve it!
Look behind you.
Look at that spectacle now.
Carpets of gannets following us.
Look.
I feel like the Pied Piper of Shetland!
Mousa, the uninhabited island Tom runs the ferry to, is a nature reserve with some very special inhabitants - storm petrels.
They're tiny seabirds about the size of a sparrow and as such, they're very vulnerable to attack from daytime hunters, like gulls and skuas so they only fly in to land under the cover of darkness.
The best way for us to film them is to stay on the island, and that will mean camping with the whole family.
Unfortunately, though, conditions have taken a turn for the worse.
Wow.
Not so sure about this swell.
Tom, the skipper of the boat, is on his way.
I can see quite a lot of white water breaking off the front of the boat but if he says it's OK, then it's OK.
Hi, Tom.
Swelly old day.
How are you?
I'm fine, thanks.
How do you rate it for the other side?
Oh, no problem there.
It's a lovely day at Mousa.
Yeah?
Yes.
No, I'm not joking.
It's only 1.5 miles away, how different can it be?
Even though there's swell, there's not much wind bringing it on, he says.
I like the bouncy thing!
That was a big wave.
Of course, Tom was right - out at Mousa, it's flat calm.
Let's run up here.
The tower on the island is in fact an ancient fort called a broch.
It's over 2,000 years old.
Now it offers safety and sanctuary for nesting storm petrels.
We won't see them until it gets dark and that gives us time to organise our own accommodation.
This is the first time Savannah has been camping, spending a whole night inside a tent.
There we go.
That was quick and easy, isn't it?
Mummy, soup is ready!
After dinner, it's time to investigate the tower.
What's that?
Castle.
Who lives in the castle?
Princess.
Are you a princess?
Yeah.
OK.
The light is fading, the clouds are gathering and the storm petrels will soon start to call to their mates to guide them in from the sea.
Once they're on land, they're very clumsy so they wait for the darkest nights before risking a visit to their breeding sites.
Some people call them storm petrels but we can call them night faeries and they sing to each other.
It's dark.
It's sleepy time.
This is where the night faeries live.
But they're not talking yet.
Come in with me.
Hold my hand.
I can see in here.
Look in there, in that hole.
There'll be a little bird that lives down at the end there, somewhere.
It's called a storm petrel.
The petrels can recognise the voice of their mate who's sitting in the nest.
That's what we're beginning to hear - the voices of the brooding birds, calling their partners so they can swap incubation duties.
One is starting to talk.
Can you here it going "neh-neh"?
What are those?
(That's the night faeries. )
(The storm petrels.
They say "neh-neh.")
(Then they start singing. )
(They sound like they're giggling. )
(Little night faeries laughing. )
Both the male and female take turns to incubate the egg while their partner heads out to sea to feed, often for two or three days at a time.
They nest in the walls around here.
They nest on the beach but there's something extra-special about being inside the broch with its history and its mystery and these little voices from the ocean singing out from the walls.
I love it.
They live in this castle and they dance and they dance.
They do.
They dance in the air.
(You can hear them giggling!)
It's been almost three weeks since I filmed the rare red-necked phalaropes on the northern isles.
Now I want to return to see how those single fathers are getting on.
The females are probably long gone, and the males will be on their own with the eggs.
Marguerite and I are being helped by RSPB wardens Malkie Smith and his wife, Martha.
OK.
You lead the way.
Martha and Malkie monitor all the nests they can find of these incredibly rare birds to help with their conservation.
There are fewer than 25 males nesting here, so we've been granted special licence to film them at the nest.
Their precious eggs and the young chicks are incredibly well-hidden and could easily be crushed by a careless boot.
Just walk in the low patches again and try not to go on the tussocks.
The chicks could be on this marshy bit.
I'll walk in your footsteps.
But, fortunately, with Malkie as our guide, we know precisely where to go.
The nest is beautifully camouflaged, invisible.
With the male away feeding, we can get prepared for filming.
There's four eggs, they look like they're almost hatching.
I think we should set it up with the lipstick camera.
I'm going to use one of my mini-cams to film the nest.
But I don't want it to stand out like a sore thumb.
A bit of improvised camouflage, and we're in business.
Phalarope cam!
Now I just have to position the camera by the nest and do my best to hide it.
Working with a nest like this is always a race against time, because you don't want to keep the birds away from the nest more than a few minutes.
Almost ready.
Malkie and Martha have headed off to check other nests, and all we have to do is get the gear and ourselves into the hide - easier said than done.
Very cosy.
Got nowhere to put my leg.
He's back, he's back.
He's coming.
He's going straight in.
Go on, go on, go on.
Yes, he's on.
Beautifully camouflaged, that nest.
When he goes inside, you can't see him at all from here.
Those rings on his legs, those are colour rings that Malkie has been putting on the birds for years.
And it means he can identify them as individuals.
He's really busy on the housework!
What's Mum up to?
She's off with the girls.
Party, party, party maybe even with another bloke.
She may well lay eggs in another nest, and have another male tend another brood.
After about 40 minutes incubating the eggs, he's off again.
Being a single parent, he's got no-one to look after the eggs when he needs a meal, and he's got to do that at least once every hour.
Do you know?
I can't bear watching a nest without the adult on it.
Can you?
Because it's... just so vulnerable.
'An hour later...'
It's not funny anymore.
What's happened to him?
It's getting colder as well, there's a mist coming in.
Concerned, I call Malkie for advice.
He just went off and hasn't been back.
But Malkie has some very reassuring news.
Well I'm glad you know where he is.
He's with Malkie, at a different...
Where Malkie's doing the ringing.
Amazing.
Thank you.
He'll let me know when he's coming!
OK, Bye.
Malkie's ringing phalaropes at a different...
It's about 3.5 - 4 km.
And our male just turned up.
Two white rings and a BTO ring.
Cup of tea then?
That's what he just said, "Have a cup of tea because I can see your male".
Cup of tea time.
I feel a bit better now.
After what turns out to be two or three cups of tea, our wanderer returns.
It's great to see him back.
I can now breathe again.
And heave an enormous sigh of relief.
Because for a while there, I thought maybe he'd been nobbled by a predator.
With this being our last trip to Shetland, I can't leave without spending some time with one of my favourite animals here.
Together with my friend and local naturalist, John Campbell, I've been following a family of otters over the past few months on a remote stretch of coastline in the east.
The last time I saw them, the mother was desperately trying to get her well-grown cubs to leave home and start life on their own.
I want to find out how they're getting on, and it's not long before we spot the male cub fishing in the lagoon.
He's one of three cubs.
He's got two sisters, who don't seem to be around at the moment.
Beautiful to have him coming so close.
He's going straight across to the other shore.
I think he's going to come out.
He's calling, and that means he still wants to be with his mother.
No sign of her though.
Ah, there she is!
They're still together.
But she doesn't look happy about it.
He's so needy, this young male.
He must be 14 months old and she doesn't want him with her.
Look at her, turning on him.
This is the mother telling the cub to keep back.
All she wants to do is get away from him.
"Don't follow me, son, "You're on your own now."
That's what the whickering calling is all about.
She's got other things on her mind and he's just holding on to his mum's apron strings, saying, "Come on Mum, can I have a cuddle?".
And she's saying, "No.
You're a big lad".
He can look after himself, feed himself.
He just wants the company.
She's gone down into the holt.
He doesn't know quite where to put himself.
He's just calling his heart out.
Sounds like there another one over here.
It's another two.
It's his sisters.
That's all three cubs.
And Mum still hiding in the holt.
Going to look inside, going in the front door.
Oh, Mum is telling them all to get lost.
They're desperate to try and get back into the company of their mother.
She's having none of it.
They just can't leave her alone.
But here she comes, that's Mum coming out.
What's she going to do?
Oh and she's actually going to groom them.
She's finally relented and thought, "OK, kids, if you must".
This period of separation is so difficult for the cubs, but it's essential too, if they're to lead an independent life.
Very sweet, right, let's catch up.
They've all gone out to the sea.
After half an hour, we find one.
It's the mother.
There's no sign of the cubs.
She's managed to give them the slip.
This could well be the first time she's been alone for over a year.
No wonder she's keeping a low profile.
It will be another three months at least before she's caring for a new family.
Until then she'll be hunting for herself, alone.
And can enjoy deep, peaceful sleep.
Our time here on Shetland is coming to a close.
We've had an awesome year, getting a flavour of the place in all its moods.
And the wildlife has been first class.
But Shetland has one last natural treasure in store for us.
We've just had a call from Helen Moncrieff, the warden down at Sumburgh.
She said, orcas have just been seen off the point and heading west, on the other side of the island.
So who knows if we're going to see them, but it's definitely worth a go.
We need to get moving to see if we can catch up with them.
We're enlisting the help of Tom, the Mousa ferryman, again.
He's got a couple of hours before his next scheduled crossing.
Suddenly, more good news.
What's happened?
They've been spotted nearby.
They're off the south end of Mousa.
Excellent!
The research team can move much faster than we can in their smaller boat.
We just have to hope the killers come our way.
I think they're just off Noness, which is just around this headland.
Noness?
Apparently they're just off Noness.
Obviously watch your time for your pick-up, as well.
There's loads of time, it's only 3.30pm.
The number of killer whales that come close to shore is very small.
Groups of five or six are the most you might see, and then only if you're very lucky.
No sign just yet.
What's that?
Is that the rib there?
That's the research team.
We must be getting close.
There.
We got orcas coming towards us right now.
What we'll do is get a little bit closer and switch the engines off.
Oh, look, look, look!
We've got a bull right here.
That's the youngsters.
Look, a big group, with the male there!
We've got a gang coming in here.
Here they come.
They're coming off the stern.
They're heading this way, folks.
Look, here we go!
Right here.
That's the sound of their breath.
They're just 30 feet away.
How beautiful is that?
This is unlike anything we've ever seen before.
There are killer whales all around us.
At least 15, maybe more!
What's extraordinary here is we've got orcas all over the place.
We seem to be surrounded by them.
It looks like several different families are all meeting and greeting.
It's 4.35pm, and within an hour.
We've seen at least 20 orcas.
We now have the opportunity to get on land and see if we can catch up with the orcas from the land.
I think they're going to head off hunting now.
They looked like they were moving inshore.
We've travelled down to Sumburgh Head the most southerly point of Shetland's mainland, and quite a crowd has already gathered for this wildlife spectacle.
Beautiful.
Lovely, lovely light.
Most of the killer whales have spread out, back into the deeper waters.
But a few are still very close.
The end of a perfect day, the killer whales just offshore.
For me, it's one last contact with the island's biggest and most impressive predators.
That's it, they're off.
Personally, I'm very content.
Spending time with these magnificent animals and seeing so many is marvellous.
Being close to them...
Very fulfilling, and on a day like this - calm, blue skies, warm - it doesn't get much better.
Shetland has offered us her most precious natural treasures over the year.
And the passion that brought me and my family here in the first place has only grown deeper.
We have to leave now.
Our journey on these northern isles is over.
But their wild character, space and above all beauty, will remain with us, forever.